perfect all right hello YouTube and
Facebook we are on our second project
raising today we are discussing food so
what is that what that's gonna look like
is we're gonna spend 15 minutes
discussing our current food system what
we do personally what the world does and
what's working or not working about it
and then 15 minutes talking about what
it could look like in an omni when n2r
avaris world ten two hundred years in
the future what is like the perfect food
system looked like for us and then we're
going to spend 30 minutes talking about
the adjacent possible so what could be
done with 10,000 people and $100,000
right now and we can get started so
would anyone like to start what they do
for food what they like about it what
they don't like about it stick to like
two minutes each I can catch Edward okay
I just want to bring up a couple things
I think what we're seeing right now with
the coronavirus and everything is is
showing us how fragile our you know
supply chains are so much of our food
system depends on that sort of thing
just like the rest of our systems
you know just-in-time supply and all
these things are extremely fragile so I
would just like to praise that
particular point all right thank you
yes fragile is huge so next I have in my
house like I used to eat a lot of
takeaway and I eat a lot of processed
food because I don't have the spoons
that you can think about what to cook
let alone make it and at the same time I
don't really have some money to pay for
takeout and packaged but I also have two
things that work really well in my life
which is my collective house my
cohousing community where we eaten eat
together three times three to four times
a week where every adult shows up once a
month and cooks and cleans and I get to
show up every other meal and pay the
cost of food and I don't have
looking clean as well as there is a
non-profit grocery store here called
quest that you need a referral the shop
at but it's all of like the stuff that
all the other grocery stores would throw
out because it's damaged or about to
expire but instead of throwing it out
they donate it and then people who are
below the poverty line can buy it for a
fraction of the cost of what they would
buy so to me it had a lot more dignity
than the food bank and I get to choose
what works and what doesn't and stock it
end up being stocking up on junk food a
lot of the time but they also have
produce that needs to be used in a
couple days so that is how do I got
going on well what tends to stand out to
me is the the fact that buying junk food
is generally cheaper than buying food
that's actually good for us so I think
that that's that's an issue in terms of
you know sort of continued poverty
cycles or without punishing as well so
it's you know we need the nutrition in
order to be able to to function well to
be healthy to be prepared for something
like this growing virus because if you
you know if your immunocompromise then
you're more at risk so yeah I would like
to see I would like to see that change
in terms of stuff that's positive I mean
it's nice to be able to do the things
like online orders it's nice that there
are you know farmers markets around the
place so if you do that bit of research
you can actually go and get fresh
produce here anyway and I'm liking some
of what I'm seeing in terms of like
permaculture and you know ecosystem
regeneration and things like that where
they're focusing on providing food as
well on it so what I like about the
current system I you know it's not the
best for everyone or do you find
involved but I do like the option to get
non-local things right so being in
Canada like I can still get avocados
year-round that the pepper is nice and
you know pick your other fruit and
veggies it's nice to be able to have
that it's somewhat efficient to have you
know like the
food shipped from the farms to sort of
like in some sort of a shipping
warehouse that tends to be one of the
more efficient ways to move that sort of
like lull look stuff but it does feel
less efficient with how I think most
people still get their food which is you
know each person goes to the the grocery
store well you know eat well let's just
say every week and sort of picks through
their own stuff and then brings it home
it does seem not that efficient plus
well I do sometimes cook it also seems
less efficient for me to do the effort
of you know the the food prep and the
cook time I do like the the cohousing
that Julie mentioned where it's you know
you might cook once a week or once every
two weeks you're cooking for a bunch of
people and then all the other days you
don't have to worry about it cuz
somebody else is cooking I quite like
that approach hey now we have a bit of
an open discussion if you want as to
what is we're not working in this for
the five or so minutes and then go on to
the beautiful future we can we can
create that's maybe not possible yet but
something else they came up well I liked
a lot of what you brought up the fragile
the chunky food being cheaper is a huge
is a huge piece there was something else
that was working but I'll let someone
else talk well I think about it now
doing so like the permaculture stuff
that Katya mentioned I think that is
quite interesting and I'm sure still
plenty of room to grow both just in our
knowledge of permaculture and just in
the number of people that are actually
doing it yeah I think a permaculture and
regenerative agriculture in general is
huge because it kind of hits two birds
with one stone it acts actually works
towards sequestering carbon soils you
know regenerating ecosystems so merging
agriculture and bringing it from the
industrial model to that sort of thing I
think is really important
I remember two things one of which was
right now getting the meal delivery kits
actually don't like them because coho
seems way better but they do help me
think about what to make there has to be
a hybrid of those where like I can get
stuff delivered I have some of it in my
fridge and some of its staple and then
it knows what I'm making it helps me do
it
sorry that's getting things out of
sequence but it could be but there's
also this place looking to here called
abundance farm the people can be part of
and of course there's all those CSA
oh they're called the boxes of like you
get in with the farmer and then they
they send you boxes of food they kind of
know how many people are feeding for the
year and they plans accordingly but an
abundance farm actually has the people
who have the shares do the work as well
so you can come and you can be part of
harvesting and part of planting and
building whatever's on the farm and then
everyone has has a part playing that I
have an issue cuz I can't get out of
there I can't get out there with
transportation it takes like two hours
to get there but I love the idea of
working together in community and
growing your own food even if you're not
living there and it's just more fun
right they're not they're not having to
harvest a certain yield they're not paid
per it's just it's paid they're working
together and harvesting together and so
they shearing them into the harvest and
bounty I'd be interested to know how
much of our food is provided through
through watch we call it like the the
old model of you know sort of mass
production with you know all the
pesticides and herbicides and everything
that sort of you know destroys the soil
versus you know how much is actually
through you know the farmers markets and
through you know like some sort of an
organic approach whether it's whether
it's permaculture raw just a better kind
of better kind of farming it's it's
difficult for me to get a picture of how
much of each is happening because I've
got the interest in your soil
regeneration and so on I get to see an
awful lot of that come up in my you know
my recommended readings and things like
that and I'm sure that it's actually a
very very very small percentage and it's
just in my face all the time
all right should we go on to the next
the next phase which is what is I think
we probably know what's happening with
food I don't think any of this has been
a shock to anyone what it's fragile that
that's why this one's so much shorter
than this is but you know generally what
we concentrate on in societies like
what's broken and what's not working and
so moving on to the big huge utopian
vision of the future that we all might
be grandparents in one day does anyone
have a bit of that they would like to
share I'd like to bring up something and
that is I think it's valuable to look at
this on a meta scale and what I mean by
that is that each unique location you'll
have rural areas urban areas rural
communities urban neighborhoods
individuals the solutions going to look
a little bit different for everybody I
don't think there's one size fits all
solution for food production and food
consumption so I think it's important to
perhaps on a global scale or on a larger
scale to create kind of like the design
globally manufacturing locally on
concept for agriculture as well so if
you know places in the world that are
trying different things unique to
different locations can share that
information and knowledge and then
people can have access to that and adopt
it to their individual situation or
individual location I think that's would
be part of the solution for me
absolutely I envision a world of shared
shared technology that that it feeds
back into the system but also my own
data feeds back into the system as I
think I'm gonna eat something and buy it
or I don't think I buy it in my utopian
future but I was involved in the
production of it and I have my food I
can also register what I throw or what I
didn't use all of I would love someone
else to do the executive functioning of
I pick my meals and it tells me what
what works for me and my family went
doesn't last time
made that this got thrown out maybe make
less of it this time your neighbors
making it let's let's share up the more
we can use technology to make it as
efficient as possible as well as share
in the labor of you know if I need to
work a month on a farm every year to be
able to pay for my food I'm down with
that especially if it's if it feels good
to work there if there's music and and
festivals and things that are don't make
it feel feel arduous and having 3d 3d
farms be able to just show up and say
here's what I'm getting and robots pick
it for me and having all of these things
interwoven together where you can get
your hands in the dirt and and grow it
or you can have it produce for you and
get the recipes and everything feeds
back into it so you can know what the
yield is if I can tell you we know what
the weather is and in the system and
what the soil conditions are and then we
can put back in well you know it grew
eight tomatoes they were the best this
year and I can coordinate with my
neighbors so if I do I grow 20 Tomatoes
I can I can give them to my to my
neighbors maybe they grow too many
watermelons and find a way to
interchange the things they truly cannot
grow here like even if we could grow
bananas in during Canada I still feel
like it makes more sense to grow them
somewhere else and ship them here
because they're a huge tree but maybe
not maybe that's taking up a lot of a
lot of their real estate and
transportation so that's a bit of my how
I would like to see oh and tailor made
to me that also like my toilet is smart
and so it knows what nutrients are
staying in my body and knows how to like
help me pick a diet that does work for
me that's not one-size-fits-all and
petri dish meat so I don't have to eat
animals but can get little big good
sorry well that last bit sounds
wonderful I think one of the things I'd
like to see is a bit more a bit more of
a resilience spread of food so that you
know we have more in the way of
community gardens that there are more
you know fruit trees on the street that
there are more you know vegetable
gardens that the people sort of allow
access to to each other
it used to been in Australia I think
like in the
you know like straight after the
Depression era that people would have
you know fruit trees in their front yard
and I didn't have the fences and all
that kind of thing and it was the way
that they were sort of working together
to sort of make sure that you know
everybody on the street was was fed I
think I would like to see more of that
and less of less of the shipping I think
that we've just gotten comfortable with
you know with it with the idea of
shipping things from around the world
and I don't know that we should be doing
so much of it like some of it sure that
you know by and large I'd like to see a
lot more a lot more local a lot more
free you know simply because it's it's
the effort that's going in rather than
the money going in yeah I think that'll
do me you guys would cover the rest of
it I definitely like the idea of having
more food being nearby both the free and
the paid versions just so that we're
less reliant on transportation like the
shipping and that sort of thing if
there's any issues there then all of a
sudden we lose the ability to feed
ourselves
I do like an emphasis on sort of not to
like really manufactured food with a
bunch of preservatives but yeah I think
pretty much everyone knows and agrees
like that's not great for you but we do
it anyway because it's easy and usually
cheaper and so to build a system that
will either you know allow if you really
want to cook that system to make it a
bit I guess easier both from the
shopping that I think what gets wasted
possibly doing something useful with the
waste but my goal is always to sort of
have people do what they're good at I'm
not necessarily good at cooking so I
feel like you know I could spend three
hours to make something that somebody
who's good at cooking could do it half
an hour and do a better job at so I
prefer to have sort of systems where
there's an emphasis on local and almost
like a meal subscription plan where it's
again not profit centered so I'm not you
know trying to buy some new
Hoover eats person yacht but rather just
the price of food plus you know 5 or 10%
I know I guess and the labor and whatnot
understanding of that would probably
mean you wouldn't have the full menu of
options if somebody is if there's some
sort of a meal plan it's probably just
gonna be a couple of options but if the
food is good and the price is reasonable
that is fine with me
and then for food that like you know
trying to get Mikado's in canada in in
winter I do think that the price on that
should probably be the real price so
right now you know we tend to sort of
not price for the the pollution and the
shipping in it and everything else
involved with shipping you know avocados
from whatever they can grow to all over
the world and all the other fruits and
veggies that we're used to getting the
baby we in Canada shouldn't be used to
getting year-round I think that's still
available but just the price is real so
you know if we can grow avocados in the
summer great that's a reasonable price
if we lose the ability ok avocados you
know they might be available but they
might be five or ten dollars a piece so
if you really want them it's an option
but probably there's going to be less of
that I achieve unless that stupid said
we find some way to grow bananas in
Canada we're never gonna be stuck on a
lot less food in Canada but yeah we also
this this you know we can open up and
I'll I'll talk about the future twenty
years from now I mean I think for me
eating in season is also a part of it
that it's better for our bodies it's
better for the planet but if it's
available in stores I'm gonna buy it and
I'll still will buy it but to be able to
price it to know that well if I'm
getting abaca dough's there's a lot more
labor I'm putting into the system or
money I'm putting into the system when
they're when they're not available but I
maybe you can get blackberries
year-round because they can grow indoors
but then you should I be eating it and
that's part of the tailor making for my
body is is being able to track those
things with with my health which of
course isn't food specifically but I'm
sure we will talk about that when we
when we saw it when we solution raised
health care and health
so that comes back to I'm thinking of
like prices as an information signal
that you know that tells you what's the
you know what's the better thing to do
this is the the worst thing to do you
know if you if you've got all of the
costs of of transport and what happens
to the environment and so on actually
included in a food product and it's
going to end up being a lot more
expensive than the version of you know
walking down the street and you know
plucking something out of the community
garden you know so one is better for the
local area probably better in terms of
health and season and all that kind of
thing that should be a lot cheaper and
easier I'm thinking and you know in in a
society where you're trying to align
what works for each person with what
works for the whole then just sort of
focusing on having everything available
so like you still want to have it
available but you should be able to know
the choice that you're making is a good
one so Nick came up earlier talking is
there some people who have a very
restricted diet who either be due to
health concerns like allergies or
something like autism where they just
can't you know they want the same thing
every day and I feel like if that's you
you should you shouldn't necessarily
have to pay 15 bucks for an avocado but
there was a way to know that right
because it's like well no if you eat an
avocado every day and it's very clear
you do that and that's basically all you
do it's like avocado on toast then yours
can be somewhat offset by other people's
yeah or help you find other things or
maybe we do grow a picado locally for
you right having it be like you're more
more a lot of those things and if
everyone wants to have a keto everyday
then we figure we figure that out how
many do we need to grow locally yeah
well maybe at the other end you just
have more money available to be able to
buy the things that you need also
I think to putting a couple things
together here um you know consuming food
closer to where it's produced and
thinking of special diets for people
there's also technologies so you know
you're trying to do things via
permaculture but there's also
technologies that allow you to grow
avocados indoor vertical farming and
stuff so I think it's a real mix of
different methodologies modalities and
pricing to have choice but also not
externalize that choice via you know
transportation thousand-mile
transportation you know and that sort of
thing one of the things we didn't
explicitly bring up during the first
part which I do want to now bring up in
the positive is like zero slave labor
nobody is and meeting also just really
low labor nobody has to work 80 hours a
week with their kids in the field to be
able to feed themselves in order for us
to get that offset externality right
like anything that's available to me for
Canadian especially Canadians we just
talked about bananas like anything
that's available for a Canadian and at
that that labor point is also available
around the world for people and to be
able to help them grow that and do that
right than any anywhere any anyone
anywhere in the world can come together
with their community and find a system
for growing food together that is the
most efficient that is greenhouses and
3d farming and permaculture and that the
rest of the world can help them whether
that looks like financing earlier on
helping do a barn raising type thing of
building it or just I want to know that
my my bounty of my life doesn't come
from the cost of somebody else's
except that wait that's another thing so
if you've got the technology in there to
sort of talk about what stocks are
everywhere of everything and you can
kind of you know go in the same way as
you know as at the moment I use Google
all the time to say such-and-such near
me and you know and I find that but I
don't have the kind of information that
might help in terms of you know what's
the what's the cheapest nutritious meal
that I could create at the moment based
on the stocks that are that are
available and to be able to pick up
things that might otherwise get thrown
out yeah and to be able to I have people
in my life especially in the community
who were amazing at that even to the
point where denoise be like I do we just
made I was cooking on Monday and we made
rice and I made way too much and then
the guy was cooking Witten got rice out
of the freezers like we need to use this
first cuz it was made first like no but
this looks fresh but like he's amazing
at knowing what's there in rotating it
and his partner's the one who knows
what's like being grown right there and
how to and to be able to use that
informations I just didn't even think
that there was rice in the freezer I
wouldn't have made it to begin with
right so good to know those kind of
things like what do I have on hand here
what's nearby at the local store and I'm
you know no I don't want to eat that
actually but yes that that sounds like
having 2 or 3 options of the local
produce that is high soft would be
amazing even more so now I'm thinking of
connecting with the neighbors where
because everyone not everyone but a lot
of people would want that right the
cheap easy high stock food and so if
you're all saying yes I'm gonna cook
that recipe it actually can say hey how
about you cook it too I'm assuming I'll
live in the same neighborhood you cook
it today Kylie and I'll cook one later
right like you whether that's just a
gift and you're like yeah I'm good at
cookie and say I have the spoons or
whether in literal spoons energy because
it's lower do more difficult or um and
then another day you don't have it right
you're like hey who has extra
dude who made an extra Portia and I my
food burns and I couldn't ride just
don't have the energy right to be able
to kind of help each other in those in
those areas with this much trust built
in as we need right if I need to see
that Kylie isn't on her coach not doing
anything and choosing not to is
everyone's really scared people will do
then I can I can be like oh look she
cooked for four other people last week
yeah I'm good with cooking for her now
that she's got the flu if we need that
in there how much you Adriel what is
your beautiful future look like jerky
sure he already did but for the
long-term
yeah sure of it right and also move on
to the the adjacent possible now if so
can we have five seconds of silence I'm
ready
I think the adjacent possible like what
I was talking about sort of having the
emphasis on local cooking and somebody
else do it I think that could sort of be
the next step people are already used to
ordering food on their phones you know
and like skip the dishes and nuber eats
I think you could make a sort of
schedule that we're instead of it being
like you you're sort of paying a premium
because you're getting it from a
restaurant and you want it right now if
you were able to set some kind like sort
of a ubereats the skipty dishes meets
like a meal planning service where you
don't have a full you know menu from
every restaurant your area there might
be ten things in a given week and you
say okay I'm gonna you know eat that in
the week and sort of build your plan
around that and then you would just get
a delivery where instead of it being you
know two pizzas it's like a bunch of
pre-made meals that you've thrown the
fridge or the freezer and it's not
priced at restaurant level on the you
wouldn't have to charge as much for
these shipping is it there would be an
emphasis on for example like oh we
deliver food to your apartment building
on Thursdays so everybody in the
building orders and then the one person
just you know as a probably a trolly
good going around and you know it's a
much easier delivery and emphasis on
making it efficient and that's more
cost-effective if that's how people act
you want to be themselves just all day
every day yeah I'd like having also am a
commercial kitchen just like we do it at
cohousing where if they don't have a
commercial kitchen but you know you're
cooking and shopping once you're
shopping cooking cleaning up once per
rounds generally for two different meals
and they're doing that on a grander
scale of like okay we're doing kind of
the the prep food of dishes hopefully
without the the waste because there's a
lot of waste that comes with those but
when you're knowing that it's getting to
get delivered to your neighborhood every
two days because there's enough people
in your neighborhood like it's about
meeting these thresholds and then having
that that happened so I know that I have
the stockpile of balsamic vinegar and
olive oil and then they just deliver the
other end and we can even have it more
delivered like things are cut up because
we've participe
or we've offset offset our labor with
money so at a fair and decent wage right
so I might put in twenty hours a month
and get my food for free or I might put
in five hours and get my food at cost
like whatever it happens to be right or
I might think I don't have any time and
so I'll pay a little bit of a premium
for not contributing labor in every
level right whether that's going to the
store and buying it and doing the
shopping online whether it's sorting it
whether it's cutting it or well
transporting it like whatever you want
to do as long as there's not a surplus
of Labor in that area and everybody
wants to Anna's want to do another that
and that can be a metric right that that
switches around driving is really
everyone loves it so that when you put
in an hour and five minutes for instead
of an hour I think too closing some
loops with waste composting so I mean
that could even happen in an urban
environment so you know if everyone can
have food delivered you can also have
waste taken away and cycle back into the
the growing system yeah and for 10,000
people that actually I like that
especially if you've got the regular
like here's here's your food give me
your waste off to the next place here's
your food give me your weight off to the
next place
right that's super efficient I like it
yeah I want the waste in the same car
through people there's two separate
parts right but having like we have
compost pickup in Vancouver and it's
both gross and good it's like a little
grossed out of it like I think to some
degree for having local farming happy
local compost is good the same guy did
the rice thing else it was amazing
compost he would be like always he's
like out there with gloves on picking up
the compost it's like his meditation I
don't know if every every neighborhood
is gonna be lucky enough to have one of
him but one of the other things is like
for me I don't feel confident in growing
a garden so I would really love to have
a app that helps me with that that
actually literally is like the Sun like
here's my here I can just do a 3d cat
and this is not a hundred thousand it's
a little over the top but it can start
with a beta right where it's just hey we
know from Google Maps where your where
your house is and we assume the Sun is
here plant your what do you want and
then here are the companion plants and
then if I can feed that information back
into the system and my neighbors use it
and so if I have a surplus of something
I can offer it to them or my raspberries
come up earlier than theirs or I didn't
even think I could grow raspberries and
then my neighbor has a has a bounty and
next year you know I'm I'm help with you
can help with seed sharing and soil
regeneration soil testing and to know to
water it right now I'm gone for a week
but my neighbors also there can someone
water mine and gives me an alert on my
phone to water it when I forgot it's
extra hot today you might want to water
it twice or water it here and doing
things like that that are adjacent
possible that's not that difficult
there's also a level of automation that
can be introduced with technology like
farmbot so far bot is really cool for
you know it can be use in a community
garden that can be used in a backyard
and basically it's all open source and
you know you don't have to actually if
you don't want to do the playing you
don't have to it's automated and the
information to share and further
information to be shared of the type
that you're talking about
reminded of a conversation I had with
say a young young guy elsewhere in
Australia last year he's talking about
getting into you know into farming but
he didn't have any kind of land in order
to do it so we were talking about this
possibility of having sort of a almost
like a and a Commons app set up such
that people who have land but don't want
to garden could set aside a certain
amount and say you know how I've got
some you know ten square metres of land
here that's you know that I'm happy for
other people to you know garden for me
and that they would then get you know
like a box of food or something you know
every so often as well so that way it
could sort of be a group of people who
are interested in you know in doing all
of that tending and the composting and
all that kind of thing who could then
run and you know like a whole
neighborhood if you like to cover sort
of all needs and then distribute our
food to anybody who is participating or
sell at markets or whatever the case may
be with the both kind of excited about
that as a concept but one of the other
things is um just tracking like what I'm
buying where and especially that's an
easier thing to track if I literally
just take a picture of what's on my
conveyor belt and my receipt and it's
somehow matches it up again not a
hundred thousand it would be more people
who want to match it up - no - and then
it learns from there but and then as
that continues you're able to see at
what point it makes sense to grow our
own or to produce our own crackers or
whatever it might be or just bulk buy it
together right I think one of the first
things that probably doesn't need to be
there when we have the infrastructures
grocery stores then if I can get it
delivered to me and I don't need it to
sit there and they're paying for rents
and I'm driving there and driving back
and getting the coronavirus from you
then we can you like it's it's a lot
more convenient to have it delivered
it's actually shown to be more
environmentally friendly I believe that
everyone getting their groceries
delivered to their door for and again
that's something we could share in the
labor of it's not 0f
to do that someone has to organize it
I'll put some plastic bags but having
that not sorting or you're just both
buying and then sorting it together and
you're able to know like if you really
want Cheerios maybe get Cheerios but if
you if you switch to this cereal it's
way less because it's the most popular
and we can multiply it in in large
quantities and it would be you know
warehouse and ten thousand people could
absolutely do that in a sustainable way
that they then if they invited the rest
of their City there would be no grocery
stores in that city rather soon which is
scary if it's owned by somebody else or
a conglomerate but if we own it and
everything's it costs as long as the
producers of the food are still there we
don't need the middleman I think it is
important like there's an element that I
would like to see well I'm all about
technology and the efficiencies there I
also don't want our food to rely on it
so something like you know you have an
app that teaches you Hale do this and
water this and that but I think before
you get to that step you have like an
encyclopedia of here's how to grow
tomatoes here's how to you know get
seeds from Tomatoes here's how to root
like the end to end of what you would
need to be able to plant yourself at you
know kind of become a farmer if you had
to and then to make sure that there are
sort of local printed copies of that
wherever possible so it was an app that
makes it sort of you don't bit easier
and more efficient anybody can do it and
then there's sort of some local printed
copies of here's how to grow it here's
how harvest seeds here's all the stuff
that you need to know just set up your
own sort of renewable food system
without the use of any technology and to
know who that person is not necessarily
like but like who in your community is
the bet is the best at growing food who
has that no information in their head
because I those books exist those books
exist at cohousing I'm so like sorry
where do I grow my money like to be able
to get that guidance but I would be able
to learn through somebody else and
through an app and then to know to
always have that conversation and we
can't be too reliant on this technology
right I guess we all starve now the
Internet's down yes make sure you know
we have an absolutely when ours is down
if it isn't a global thing all
the internet goes down like a solar
flare or something that we we know who's
Edie and who is not and we can ship food
to them when needs be even if we are
trying to stay local like we don't let
our communities neighboring communities
starve right that's not tangential
tomorrow sadly but I think it actually
is adjacent possible to have an
understanding of what food growing
systems are out there and which ones
produce the highest like yield for every
individual like the geography right for
the climate and it's a degree analysis
it outside as a 3d farming is a
permaculture and can you have a
combination but if the community wants
to grow what's gonna be their most
efficient if we're feeding that back
into the system the information and
sharing the intellectual resource that
can be very powerful I like not having
it all in in the technology system I was
actually just thinking it might be a
good you know for the early part of
schooling to not just have you know like
the reading writing and arithmetic but
growing hell yes yeah that definitely
should be a part of school II like them
I don't think probably anyone here has
really had proper schooling in how to
grow your own food you know how to
survive if there is a grocery store to
go and buy stuff from and then also
probably an important thing is to figure
out you know which seeds are our
Terminator seeds and which things have
sort of been made to not be long-lasting
and make sure that we're not doubling in
that area cuz that's incredibly did that
seems incredibly did dangerous for sort
of long-term being able to feed a
community and not being reliant on the
overall system is like oh yeah but you
can only grow those Tomatoes for three
generations and then they're gonna stop
knowing who's who's holding the hair
looms right blue hands like not because
you have to but because hey you're
really passionate about heirloom
tomatoes we know where to go for
heirloom seeds cuz right you're that
person yeah a good girl and greens as
well like in in an area one have many
different breeds so it's not just to
have some of the seeds ratified by some
people but to
you know Lee intentionally have 30
different varieties of tomatoes growing
right totally what are the other things
I love about a gardening app is that I
can get real-world advice for it's like
hey this bugs on here yeah cool that's
fine that bug is eating your other
buttons hey brown stuff this is your
watering it too much you're not watering
it up you are like to actually get
real-time information so I don't have to
wait so I don't get in a yield it can
actually help me while I'm going and I'm
willing to reach out and kind if people
are willing to do that labor right to
say yes I'm a gardener I know what that
is that would be great and hey maybe
there's someone who cultivates ladybugs
right who's like I have ladybugs for you
I you can if you have a Fitz come get
some baby ladybugs they don't fly away
God be cool artists and all that I think
for the next step it does seem like a
lot of these are components that you
would definitely want to solve as soon
as possible I think that like oh sure if
somebody said it here or this is just in
all the conversations that you and I
have had on this topic do movie but
something like the you know the meal
delivery app starting up by identifying
sort of areas that are interested in
areas that have like kind of a soup
kitchen mmm nearby that could act as the
commercial kitchen and then you can also
say hey while we're here maybe five to
ten or or more percent ends up staying
in the soup kitchen to two feet almost
people but then you are dealing with
much bigger volumes of food and you know
and making that same use of the time and
you're sort of also been in that area
once you get that established and you
have either you know people
participating or ideally in the early
stages just paying customers then you
can you know either seek to expand
and/or say oh we're actually in a good
setup with this soup kitchen there's a
plot nearby that we could buy and start
to you know like set up a community
garden where the end goal is you'd start
with just the sort of the system as we
have it where the soup kitchen will just
go and buy the ingredients either from a
grocery store or if they can swing it
and have the connections from local
farmers and then use that either try and
set up more of
those spots or starting to actually grow
your own food and starting to track that
that seems sort of like the next step
from where we're starting now yeah I
think there's there's next steps in all
of these places right there's like how
we grow food together the next step
there's how we like the labor we put
into our food already right even if
we're disconnected from it we go to the
grocery store we prep it we you know
have to clean up after it to be able to
content it make that more efficient to
have a recipe sharing to have that
knowledge base and then also the end
right that we want the compost we wanted
to go back into the system and stay
there and then I kind of adjacent is
also like all of the packaging and stuff
that's there right if we can have a
conversation about packaging and what is
currently being done like restaurants I
eat a restaurants a lot I like the idea
of being able to plan my life ahead of
time let's say a week in advance or a
couple weeks in advance and get a
discount because I'm saying hey I know
I'm getting pizza this day right they're
like okay if you're eating pizza on
Saturday then you if you get it
delivered at 6:00 in your neighborhood
you get it you get a 15 20 percent
discount right or whatever because
you're sharing in that delivery thing
maybe the delivery driver gets more to
be able to say okay well pad thai like
restaurant if they know they're making
thirty pad thai dishes they can do it
much more efficiently than doing it on a
one-off basis right and having those
conversations at the restaurant of like
what could you offer this and having
them say like five things the collective
house that I'm part of the common house
having that be made available in
churches and schools anywhere that does
have a commercial kitchen if they want
to write to say hey this is a space we
can that isn't necessarily soup kitchens
and homeless people they're invited to
write there one of the community members
unless they have an addiction or health
challenge they're not able to cook maybe
they have hepatitis and you don't I mean
we don't we don't want it but they they
find it they clean they sweep the floor
but like it's an invitation that
everyone's equal and everyone gets to
contribute to the food and then if
someone truly doesn't they're offsetting
theirs with a lot more money right I do
I do like that because they're like
setting a percentage for how much of the
food goes to the homeless is helpful but
then also like you also kind of always
want to make it more so to actually say
hey everyone you know even if you aren't
home
you can still participate and get your
food either cheaper or free but I do it
you know by cleaning by cooking by doing
any of these things that's open to
almost people as well extra money if
they're getting paid to it like if
there's tons of people who don't have
the time right they're doctors they're
lawyers they're they're like listen it's
not worth it for me to come and put 20
like I'd rather pay someone 25 bucks an
hour to take my spot and as long as it's
done with dignity at least that's my
wanting like I don't want it to be like
tears
you're better than and I paid for it so
I get it it's like no everyone
contributes but some people have more
time to contribute they don't have money
and other people have funny and don't
have time to contribute so let's share
in that mm-hmm sorry Kylie I think here
is something I was thinking um like that
I mean that is definitely as a stick
that could be taken soon I won't they
might be you know in the in the long
term sort of more power and developing
the the resilience at the beginning of
the food chain rather than sort of at
the end of it you know it's so making
you know something that sort of more
focused on the on that gardening side or
more focused on the creation of like raw
foods and the distribution of those do
you like me like so I think meals are
important but it's kind of its kind of
assuming that all of the ingredients are
there right and they're going to come
from brittle system so yeah um that was
just what I was pondering I love the
idea of having is what I've had what I
bought cuz we have a lot of cute like
little um produce places that are close
by they have way cheaper produce and
they're mainly Indian food because
that's the neighborhood on in that being
able to know what is offered at that
local store and have somebody say oh
yeah I walked in and made this meal and
then have them be able to put that in
the system so I can be like I can just
lock it like using someone else's
intellectual labor because they're
amazing at that and I'm not to be like
oh this is in season I can make this
meal for five bucks right and that is
something that is possible but it's only
possible at the larger scale than ten
thousand Eibon need ten thousand people
in Vancouver putting their information
in for that
but we do know what's in season in
Vancouver so almost everywhere I would
have chief cucumbers at the same time or
chief whatever at the same time so
having a chef put in a system that's
like yes I can't tell you what's at your
local store and I can say this meal is
probably gonna be way cheaper than
normal and then if you work with that
with the staples we know we're almost in
everyone's kitchen if you don't have
those staples you can both buy them at
this price then we're able to do it in a
much more efficient level to say right
now that's not the growing right but
like then we're working with hey then it
can it is a very short growing seasons
we have my buy it goes more to the other
side of it but during growing season all
of your neighbors have peas right now
everyone has spinach right now here are
the things you can make with that and
you can buy it from your local your mix
next-door neighbor right there
collecting it here's the price point
they're all their food that they have
extra goes somewhere and we're selling
it out to people so you don't have to
worry about that I'm buying it for my
neighbor and I got to go get it and I
mined this from them you know making it
more efficient so Kylie when you're
talking about sort of helping up the
earliest part of the system with people
doing individual farms are you picturing
almost like a crowd farming where
instead of it being one big farm it's
off in the distance that that sends it
back and forth you just have like
anybody with a plot of land you know
there's some system that would figure
out as Julie what sort of hinting at
what to grow in and who's already
growing what's like nope we've got
enough cucumbers to thank you maybe
plant some peas where that sort of the
the first step is to replace the big
farms with you know a thousand small
farms um yes I'm not even thinking that
in terms of funds it's more like
like micro farms like not true farms but
a garden and look um there's probably
proud of this is me thinking about so
not really high-density living but you
know suburbia okay so if you actually
had a pretty good-sized backyard and
even a front yard and like quite a bit
of space to grow it yet not even huge
but just you know something we can we
could grow something right but you
knowing I think that there's a lot of
people who
I'm not interested in you know in
growing it themselves but but you know
might be interested in having their land
be made available for people to come in
growing there and in return get some of
the get some of the produce right from
yeah wait there's like you can
contribute your time and you know like
the you know skills you can also
contribute the land that you own yeah
and if it's open
it's one day he said or you own and I'm
like I rents where I am but I could say
yes you can use my backyard right as
long as I okay with you upstairs
neighbors you're legally permitted to
let people grow up yeah I just want to
share that like a cohousing and it's in
Vancouver it's some of the most
expensive lands on the planet and in
three Lots that's what they grew these
the grew they grew 40 units some 393
Lots they built but they have a green
how this like beautiful growing space
they grow in every square inch oh that
you can grow in and for about May until
October nearly every bite of solid that
we make is thrown there like next-door
neighbor we go and eat I'm like how do
we eat the blueberries from the neighbor
when like their one house and we're you
know forty or forty households whatever
but it's um you can grow a lot in an
urban area and this is an and Cooper not
even suburbia where it's everyone has
their own backyard the next-door
neighbor has a beautiful big backyard
who grows the blueberry but we've grown
on about three of those plots there was
a used to live in East Vancouver and
there was this one house that had this
really interesting setup where the
actual had a sign explaining it I think
more so that people wouldn't steal their
food but they had this really narrow
strip of land and I think they were
calling it the hundred meter diet or
something like that
um design where the idea was that a it
was like in your yards it was a hundred
meters you know from your house but it
was also like you find yourself on I
think it was 100 square meters or some
smaller I'm not that and in their front
yard in Vancouver they had like wheat
growing and like a bunch of other things
that you don't normally see grown in
Vancouver or even
in cities in general that I think like
that's sort of a a set up on a bigger
scale in suburbia could be very cool
where you're driving down a suburbia and
instead of you know just kind of the
boring manicured lawns you're seeing
like wheat and yeah and tomatoes and
peas and like people's front yards and
then who knows what their backyards are
like probably even more what I really
like about good sorry go ahead
Edward I think another thing to consider
is surplus and community resilience in
terms of preparing for disaster
you know drought or that the Cascadia
fault you know happens and so how do you
factor that in storage surplus
what do you storm you know how does that
get distributed mm I mean like to old
libraries of things like canning and
then DIY canning workshops right and we
have a surplus pic mean doing those kind
of things and knowing having a database
of that right to know that so many
pickles we have by the way the number of
people that are involved we actually
only home two days worth of food just so
we're clear like you can actually even
do that math right what what I wanted to
share was what I loved about the
gardening app idea right and knowing
this plan and knowing that I can share
with it is if it wasn't half right if it
wasn't just um I don't know on paper or
something is that I can also share my
labor when I'm capable of it right on a
day I have more spoons I can be like
who's got work for me to do right like I
could go read my neighbor's lawn right I
think I have ten minutes of time to do
and so I can do it in small bursts or I
can do you know it's it's done on my
schedule and yet it would still be
tracked and put into a system of here's
how much food I get out of it if I
needed that to happen or just hey I'm
really good putting in an hour worth of
time knowing that it feeds my neighbors
yeah yeah and within a few also up you
unlock other cool options like you know
if you're having like a crowd farming
and each individual plot has notes on
things you can do you can do
crop cycling like hey you grew corn last
year maybe a girl cabbage this year and
then you can also have an overall you
know snapshot of okay there's a thousand
farms in this you know small village
here's what each one is growing you know
you if you want to start up any one
great here's what other people are
growing here's what we need and if you
want to get fancy you could like test
the soil and figure out what might
actually grow the best there because
it's like what if the insects get the
app they're like over here
you know ants will be the first ones
little their little GPS devices instead
of 5g killing everything just all the
bugs learn how to speak the bees tell
each other the bees tell them the bees
are all over the place that's
sidetracking but ya know crop rotation
is huge and no I mean you know like both
for insects then also for nutrients
right that this one fixes the nitrogen
and part of that is like we grow in that
way even though I don't grow we grow it
that way and it's never it doesn't
really grow in the quantity you want to
use them it grows in the quantity that
works for the the ecological footprint
of those plants right so there's also
like hey we have a surplus of beans
because they're nitrogen fixing but
we're not eating enough beans we can
find a way to eat more beans or we can
also use that to pay for pay to feed
animals right to be like hey we have
excess excess food we can put this into
that or and that animal so we can grow
chickens locally and goats and in the
short trade that in you know just
typical game a like we have a ton of
beans I've really want some avocados
right like and just do it it just a
regular sell our beans for money and use
the money to buy other cars and I think
once you've got a network of that going
you could also do like property nerve
work if you know because we're in
Vancouver a no sir
a certain corn season we just have
cucumbers all year long maybe in an area
where for whatever reason they can't
grow cucumbers but they have you know
good berries or apples or something you
could start to set up sort of medium to
long term shipping but it's sort of
meant as more of like a trade like hey
we're gonna send you two truckloads full
of beans please send those to truffles
pull apples and well it's not ideal for
like a long-term shipping perspective it
does help unlock some of that other food
that maybe you wouldn't be able to have
in probably the most ideal way possible
yeah I think we should wrap up this
section possibly by saying what we think
is the most powerful adjacent possible
that we talked about you don't need to
pick any one you can pick the same one
and then I think for me I like the idea
of something sort of like you know
scheduled food app for something like
uber eats where it's actually helping
people save money and eat better and at
the same time that organization or app
or whatever is starting to gain money so
that it can then go you know and buy
some garden plots or start to sort of
grow in its in its purpose with you know
still mostly playing by game a rules I
can say mine
I'm for me my in my life what I would
find most powerful is a way for the
recipe sharing to know what I can I can
afford with both my spoons and my money
to be able to know what I can create and
then be able to coordinate with my
neighbors and other people to bring that
purchasing power up even though I do
think the most powerful is the gardening
yeah for be oh that's okay yeah just to
start some test projects on you know
maybe something in an urban environment
something in a rural environment and
just start sharing information I don't
think it's quite that crazy if that
makes sense it's like the data that you
would need at the level of you know
recipe sharing or if you know like
wanting a particular kind of meal or
something on those lines that could
fairly easily flow up from the what do
we have from this gardening that we're
all doing what are we missing that we
might be able to trade on what do we
have a lot of and you know people
putting in there this is how I'm using
it that's then there next when you put a
you know like a surplus of the same
thing and you know the oh we can do this
so we preserved this and this is how to
do it and then you've got a you know
like when you have a fair bit of that
information and if you have something
that sort of community community based
in terms of gardening you can also pull
in the education for kids you know like
that a you know that it could be like
whether it's some part of normal school
system or just a you know like everybody
bringing kids along for lecture of days
gardening or something like that so I
think you know it's like I like all of
the ideas I'm just wondering whether
they actually needed to be separate or
whether you could
one thing that kind of just grows and
flows sort of from that you know from
the beginning to to the end I think we
absolutely can have it all and I like
that that they do all mean but it's
starting with one data that would be a
hundred thousand dollars right so it
would be prioritizing what's the most
impactful we have and then yeah clearly
like I want it to go down to the growing
the food and up to the efficiency of my
neighbors and working with schools and
making sure everyone in my neighborhoods
fed and ya know we can do this like this
that's what this project raising our
sorry solution raising is is like this
was possible right like not maybe the
four of us but if there were ten
thousand people putting in ten dollars
we could create a food app that we owned
together and it continually get better
and better and who wouldn't want to use
that
who wouldn't want to use a recipe
sharing app that I could even like with
just in database of recipes is huge like
they exist everywhere online but that I
could be like hey I'm gluten free how do
you make this into gluten free how do
you make this into peanut free how do I
have these seven people come you know
they all have different dietary
restrictions give me a freaking recipe I
can make yeah there's a lot of
improvement to be made in the area of
recipes and meal planning and stuff that
like the same recipe hooked everyone
does it the same way and it's the most
like it doesn't help with the planning
your meals and like going out shopping
for it it doesn't really help with the
like knowing what to group together you
have to kind of read through the recipe
and figure out okay so I can put these
things in the same bowl and these things
in the same bowl there could very easily
be an app that would help you from end
to end
yeah you say like okay I'm in an area
that has these you know cheap and
plentiful ingredients please help me
plan meals using these ingredients
heavily and then from these things like
you you build your meal plan and then it
just says okay you have to go and buy
eight pounds of onions and you know
twelve pounds of potatoes and that
spread across 30 different recipes but I
don't know any app that even comes close
to doing that kind of thing I think
something kind of like adjacent to the
idea of like the the app that would help
you sort of schedule meals being
delivered is something I've been trying
to figure out how to do in my building
is I live in an apartment and I'm not
all that tidy and so I've always thought
like could you get a housekeeper for
cheaper if you for example lived in an
apartment building and there was ten
other people or thirty other people in
your building or on your floor that also
needed the same service and fit schedule
like Oh Wednesday is when our floor
housekeeper comes if you want in on it
you know you can get twenty or twenty
five percent off that housekeeper you
know has a bunch of work available and
only has to travel the ones block yeah
the bar we can create a central thing
McKee yeah don't solve it a new problem
it's a whole other solution so you know
it's it's the same sort of identify a
need whether it's a scheduled meal or
you know I shared you know both
housekeeping sort of having people raise
their hand in area say I'd be interested
and then once you hit a certain
threshold you say great you know the
housekeeper that I you know that we're
that we're working I said as long as we
have ten people we can get it for X
price cool we just hit ten people let's
start doing that oh the soup kitchen and
group that have you talked to says that
we need you know a hundred people in
this area in its neighborhood to
participate let's start gathering them
yeah absolutely I don't think that's ten
thousand I think that's like when we
have more people because that Jubilee
I did not jus believe do you believe
like the threshold of flipping we're
like if we have ten million people who
are willing to not pay dead not accept
dead we can cancel that right that's the
energy or I don't know what the level is
but yeah having that so that it's like
this is the threshold you need to start
a to a library in your city here's the
threshold you need to start anything
here in your community and then having
people a working group of those people
to be able to create it but I think
we're getting into different solutions
now we already fixed food we've moved on
next so you know said I wanna see more
burning stuff to say we all say goodbye
to YouTube and Facebook have a quick
wrap-up all right goodbye Facebook
goodbye YouTube you're welcome we fix
food for you